<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
]>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     category="info"
     docName="draft-schemacommons-aaif-00"
     ipr="trust200902"
     submissionType="independent"
     xml:lang="en"
     version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="AAIF">Autonomous Agent Interchange Format (AAIF)</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schemacommons-aaif-00"/>

    <author initials="B." surname="van Bussel" fullname="Bob van Bussel">
      <organization>Observalytics SL</organization>
      <address>
        <email>bob@observalytics.com</email>
        <uri>https://github.com/Observalytics-SL</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2026" month="June"/>
    <area>ART</area>

    <keyword>AI agents</keyword>
    <keyword>multi-agent systems</keyword>
    <keyword>LLM</keyword>
    <keyword>interoperability</keyword>
    <keyword>agent portability</keyword>
    <keyword>JSON Schema</keyword>
    <keyword>Model Context Protocol</keyword>
    <keyword>orchestration</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        The Autonomous Agent Interchange Format (AAIF) is an open, vendor-neutral
        specification for the portable definition of artificial intelligence agents.
        An AAIF document encapsulates an agent's identity, goal, system instructions,
        large language model (LLM) provider preferences and fallback routing,
        multi-agent orchestration topology (sequential pipeline, parallel swarm,
        dynamic routing, and mid-run handoff), tool catalogue (supporting function,
        MCP, HTTP, and OpenAPI protocols with structured authentication), memory
        configuration, runtime policy, OpenTelemetry telemetry settings, LLM-as-judge
        evaluation criteria, and compliance controls including data residency and
        human-in-the-loop approval.
      </t>
      <t>
        An agent defined in AAIF can be validated offline, committed to version control,
        and imported into any conforming runtime regardless of the original authoring
        environment.  This document describes the AAIF data model, field semantics,
        conformance levels, capability negotiation protocol, and the companion Agent
        State checkpoint schema that enables cross-platform live migration of running
        agents.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="introduction" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
        The multi-agent LLM platform ecosystem, as of mid-2026, comprises more than
        a dozen actively developed frameworks: LangGraph, CrewAI, AutoGen, Open WebUI,
        Cline, Semantic Kernel, BeeAI, Haystack, DSPy, Agno, and the native agent APIs
        of OpenAI, Anthropic, and Google.  Each framework has defined its own concept
        of an agent and its own storage format.  An agent authored for LangGraph cannot
        be imported into CrewAI.  A definition written for Open WebUI is unreadable by
        AutoGen.  Every platform has solved the same problem in an incompatible way,
        and the developer is the primary victim of that incompatibility.
      </t>
      <t>
        This fragmentation has direct operational consequences.  Agent definitions
        encode business logic: the instructions that shape an AI's persona, the
        constraints that prevent harmful actions, the tools the agent may call and the
        authentication credentials it uses, and the compliance rules it must follow.
        When that logic is locked inside a proprietary format, it cannot be audited
        independently, cannot be migrated without manual recreation, and cannot be
        shared across team boundaries that use different tooling.  An agent definition
        is becoming a new kind of compliance artefact, with the same importance as a
        data processing agreement or terms-of-service document.  It deserves the same
        portability.
      </t>
      <t>
        Analogous fragmentation problems have been solved before.  Database connectors
        fragmented until ODBC.  Email clients fragmented until SMTP and MIME.  Calendar
        applications fragmented until iCalendar <xref target="RFC5545"/>.  Container
        deployments fragmented until the Open Container Initiative image format.  In
        every case, the industry converged on a shared definition format because the
        cost of incompatibility became high enough that a neutral standard was the
        rational choice for all parties.  The multi-agent LLM market is approaching
        that inflection point.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document specifies the Autonomous Agent Interchange Format (AAIF), a
        portable, vendor-neutral definition format for AI agents.  AAIF standardises
        the declaration of an agent — its identity, capabilities, and constraints —
        not its execution loop, so that a definition created in one runtime can be
        imported and executed in any other conforming runtime.
      </t>

      <section anchor="requirements-language" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>
          The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
          "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>",
          "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>",
          "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
          "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and
          "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
          described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
          when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="scope" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Scope</name>
        <t>
          AAIF is in scope for: agent name, goal, and system instructions; LLM
          provider preferences and multi-provider fallback routing; tool catalogue
          with protocol and authentication declarations; memory backend configuration;
          multi-agent orchestration topology; runtime policy (timeout, retry, concurrency);
          telemetry endpoints; evaluation criteria and golden test cases; compliance
          controls (data residency, PII handling, human-in-the-loop approval, audit
          logging); and agent provenance including cryptographic signature.
        </t>
        <t>
          AAIF is out of scope for: the agent execution loop itself; billing and
          metering; provider-specific internal optimisations; and streaming response
          wire formats between an agent and an end user (as opposed to agent-to-agent
          state handoff, which is in scope for the Agent State schema described in
          <xref target="agent-state"/>).
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="terminology" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Terminology</name>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>AAIF document</dt>
        <dd>
          A JSON (or CBOR, see <xref target="binary-encoding"/>) instance conforming
          to one of the three AAIF schemas: agent definition, Agent State, or platform
          manifest.
        </dd>
        <dt>Agent definition</dt>
        <dd>
          The primary AAIF document type: the complete portable declaration of one
          agent, validated against agent.schema.json.
        </dd>
        <dt>Producer</dt>
        <dd>
          Software that emits AAIF documents (an exporter from a native agent
          framework).
        </dd>
        <dt>Consumer</dt>
        <dd>
          Software that imports an AAIF document and executes or enforces it (a
          runtime).
        </dd>
        <dt>Conformance level</dt>
        <dd>
          One of the seven cumulative conformance levels defined in
          <xref target="conformance"/> that a Producer or Consumer claims.
        </dd>
        <dt>Condition</dt>
        <dd>
          The structured-or-string routing and gating type used in orchestration
          handoff conditions, subagent selection predicates, event filters, and
          human-in-the-loop triggers.  See <xref target="conditions"/>.
        </dd>
        <dt>Capability</dt>
        <dd>
          A dot-namespaced runtime feature string an agent may declare as required
          via agent.required_capabilities[] and a platform may advertise in its
          Platform Manifest.  See <xref target="capability-negotiation"/>.
        </dd>
        <dt>Platform Manifest</dt>
        <dd>
          A machine-readable AAIF document (platform-manifest.schema.json) published
          by a runtime that declares its supported capabilities, conformance level, and
          intake endpoint.
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="design-principles" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Design Principles</name>
      <t>AAIF is built on seven design principles:</t>
      <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
        <li>
          <strong>Declare, don't bind.</strong>  Model and tools are preferences;
          Consumers <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> substitute equivalent alternatives when the
          declared option is unavailable.
        </li>
        <li>
          <strong>Provider-agnostic routing.</strong>  The fallback chain and routing
          strategy express intent across any LLM provider without hard-coding one.
          The consumer implements the routing layer.
        </li>
        <li>
          <strong>Tool-protocol agnostic.</strong>  Function, MCP <xref target="MCP"/>,
          HTTP, and OpenAPI tool protocols are supported in a unified tool object.
        </li>
        <li>
          <strong>Safety first-class.</strong>  Constraints and compliance fields are
          normative; Consumers <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> enforce them.  Silent constraint
          stripping is a conformance violation.
        </li>
        <li>
          <strong>Composable.</strong>  Context schema references can point at other
          open standards; orchestration subagent references link to other AAIF
          definitions by UUID or URI.
        </li>
        <li>
          <strong>Verifiable.</strong>  The provenance.signature field allows Consumers
          to cryptographically verify an agent's origin before execution.
        </li>
        <li>
          <strong>Observable by default.</strong>  Telemetry and evaluation blocks are
          first-class fields, not optional afterthoughts.  Observability is opt-out,
          not opt-in.
        </li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="document-structure" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>AAIF Document Structure</name>
      <t>
        An AAIF agent definition is a JSON object validated against the AAIF agent
        schema (JSON Schema draft 2020-12 <xref target="JSON-SCHEMA"/>).  The minimum
        conformant document requires only three fields:
      </t>
      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
{
  "sc_standard": "SC-006",
  "agent": {
    "name": "Example Agent",
    "goal": "Assist users with their enquiries."
  }
}
]]></artwork>

      <t>
        The full object model is organised as a tree with a root that carries
        document-level metadata, an agent block containing the operational declaration,
        and a provenance block:
      </t>

      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
AgentDefinition (root)
  sc_standard     "SC-006"  (required)
  sc_version      string (semver, default "3.4.0")
  agent_id        string (UUID, stable across import/export)
  status          draft | active | deprecated
  tags[]          string[]
  agent
    name / version / description / goal / instructions / skills[]
    required_capabilities[]   (capability negotiation, Section 7)
    model
      provider / preferred / provider_id / base_url
      fallbacks[]             (ordered multi-provider fallback chain)
      routing_strategy        cost | latency | quality | round_robin
      min_context_tokens      (routing guard)
      params / params.extended / response_format
    orchestration
      role      orchestrator | worker | evaluator | router | synthesizer
      subagents[] / handoff[] / pipeline[]
      parallel_execution / max_iterations / consensus
    context[]               (RAG sources: text / file / url / dataset)
    tools[]                 (Section 5.3)
    memory[]                (Section 5.4)
    constraints[]           (hard guardrails, enforced by runtime)
    io                      (input/output schemas, streaming, mode)
    events                  (triggers and lifecycle hooks)
    runtime                 (timeout, retries, concurrency, queue)
    telemetry               (OTEL tracing, metrics, OTLP endpoint)
    evaluation              (LLM-as-judge, metrics, test cases)
    compliance              (safety_level, data_residency, PII, audit)
  provenance
    authored_by / source_platform / created_at / updated_at
    license / sc_refs[] / signature
]]></artwork>

      <section anchor="root-fields" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Root and Identity Fields</name>
        <t>
          The sc_standard field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be the string "SC-006".  This
          serves as the document type discriminator.
        </t>
        <t>
          The agent_id field is a UUID assigned once at agent creation.  It
          <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> change on import, export, or version bump.  Consumers
          <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> use it as the canonical deduplication key.
        </t>
        <t>
          The status field reflects the agent definition's lifecycle: "draft" (under
          development), "active" (production-ready), or "deprecated" (retained for
          back-compat only).  Consumers <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> refuse to execute
          "deprecated" agents.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="model-routing" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>LLM Provider Routing</name>
        <t>
          The agent.model block expresses routing intent rather than a hard binding
          to a specific model.  A conforming Consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> implement
          the following routing algorithm:
        </t>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
          <li>
            Attempt the primary route: model.provider and model.preferred.
          </li>
          <li>
            If the primary provider is unavailable or rate-limited, walk
            model.fallbacks[] in declared order.  Each fallback entry carries its own
            provider, model identifier, and an optional cost ceiling
            (max_cost_usd_per_1k_tokens).
          </li>
          <li>
            Apply model.routing_strategy when multiple models are equally available:
            "cost" selects the cheapest model meeting min_context_tokens; "latency"
            selects the fastest by observed p50; "quality" selects the highest
            benchmark score by platform-defined ranking; "round_robin" distributes
            load evenly; "preferred_first" always tries the declared order before
            optimising.
          </li>
          <li>
            Never route to a model whose context window is smaller than
            model.min_context_tokens.
          </li>
        </ol>
        <t>
          The model.provider field enumerates 16 standard providers: openai,
          anthropic, google, vertex_ai, mistral, cohere, groq, ollama, azure_openai,
          bedrock, huggingface, together, fireworks, deepseek, xai, openrouter.
          For providers not in the enumeration (gateway proxies, self-hosted
          deployments, or new entrants), authors set model.provider to "custom" and
          supply model.provider_id (a stable string identifier, e.g. "copilot" or
          "litellm") and optionally model.base_url (an OpenAI-compatible API base URL).
          This keeps the standard open-ended without enum churn for each new gateway.
        </t>
        <t>
          The model.params.extended field is an open object that carries provider-specific
          parameters not covered by standard fields (e.g. extended thinking budget for
          Anthropic models).  The Consumer forwards these verbatim to the provider API
          and <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> validate their contents.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="orchestration" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Orchestration Topology</name>
        <t>
          AAIF defines five agent roles and four topology patterns that cover the
          majority of multi-agent LLM architectures observed in production.
        </t>
        <t>The five roles are:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>orchestrator — coordinates subagents and aggregates results.</li>
          <li>worker — executes a specific task assigned by an orchestrator.</li>
          <li>evaluator — scores or judges the output of other agents.</li>
          <li>router — examines input and dispatches to appropriate specialists.</li>
          <li>synthesizer — merges outputs from parallel workers into a single result.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>The four topology patterns are:</t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Sequential pipeline</dt>
          <dd>
            Each agent's output is the next agent's input.  Declared via
            orchestration.pipeline[] (an ordered list of subagent aliases).
            Used when tasks have clear sequential dependency order.
          </dd>
          <dt>Parallel swarm (fan-out/fan-in)</dt>
          <dd>
            An orchestrator fans out to multiple workers simultaneously; a synthesizer
            merges results.  Enabled by setting orchestration.parallel_execution to
            true.  An optional consensus mechanism (majority_vote, best_of_n, referee,
            first_success) governs how the synthesizer resolves disagreement.
          </dd>
          <dt>Dynamic routing</dt>
          <dd>
            A router agent examines the input and dispatches to the appropriate
            specialist.  Each entry in orchestration.subagents[] carries a "when"
            Condition (see <xref target="conditions"/>) that governs selection.
          </dd>
          <dt>Mid-run handoff</dt>
          <dd>
            Any agent can delegate mid-run to another agent using orchestration.handoff[].
            The handoff entry declares a Condition, a target agent reference, and flags
            controlling whether context and memory are passed to the receiving agent.
          </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          These patterns compose freely.  A pipeline step can itself be a swarm; a
          swarm worker can trigger a handoff.  The orchestration.max_iterations field
          provides a loop guard (default 10) that the Consumer
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> enforce.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="tools" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Tool Definitions</name>
        <t>
          Each entry in agent.tools[] declares a tool in one of four protocols:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>function</dt>
          <dd>
            An in-process callable.  The parameters_schema is forwarded as-is to the
            model's function-calling API (OpenAI, Anthropic, and Gemini formats are
            all compatible).  No endpoint is required.
          </dd>
          <dt>mcp</dt>
          <dd>
            A Model Context Protocol <xref target="MCP"/> server.  The endpoint uses
            the form mcp://server-name/capability or a full WebSocket/stdio URI.
            The Consumer connects to the MCP server and exposes its tools to the LLM.
          </dd>
          <dt>http</dt>
          <dd>
            A raw REST endpoint.  The Consumer constructs a request using
            parameters_schema as the request body schema.
          </dd>
          <dt>openapi</dt>
          <dd>
            An OpenAPI 3.x specification URL or local path.  The Consumer parses the
            spec, exposes all or selected operations as tools, and handles
            authentication via the spec's securitySchemes combined with the AAIF
            auth block.
          </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          Every tool entry <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> carry a structured auth block.  The
          auth.type field names the authentication mechanism (bearer, api_key, oauth2,
          aws_sigv4, basic, mtls, or none).  Secrets <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> appear
          inline in the AAIF document.  The auth.env_var field names an environment
          variable whose value the Consumer resolves at runtime.  The auth.vault_ref
          field (introduced in v2.1) provides a structured reference to a secret in an
          external vault — AWS Secrets Manager, HashiCorp Vault, Azure Key Vault, GCP
          Secret Manager, or 1Password — identified by provider, path, key, and optional
          version.  When both env_var and vault_ref are declared, vault_ref takes
          precedence.
        </t>
        <t>
          Additional per-tool fields control cache_ttl_seconds (cache successful
          responses), timeout_seconds (per-call timeout), and rate_limit
          (requests_per_minute and tokens_per_minute).
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="memory" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Memory Configuration</name>
        <t>
          AAIF distinguishes four memory scopes reflecting fundamentally different
          retention and privacy requirements:
        </t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>
            user — persists across sessions for a single user.  <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>
            be shared across user boundaries.
          </li>
          <li>
            session — scoped to a single conversation session.
            <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> outlive the session boundary.
          </li>
          <li>task — scoped to a single agentic task execution.</li>
          <li>long_term — persistent storage across users and sessions.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          Each memory entry declares a backend from the standard vocabulary:
          in_memory, redis, postgres, sqlite, pinecone, weaviate, qdrant, chroma,
          or custom.  Vector backends additionally declare an embedding_model, a
          retrieval_strategy (similarity, keyword, hybrid, or recency), and top_k
          (number of items to retrieve per query, default 5).  A ttl_seconds field
          controls expiry; zero means never expire.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="runtime" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Runtime Configuration</name>
        <t>
          The agent.runtime block declares production safety controls.  A Consumer
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> abort execution after runtime.timeout_seconds and return
          a structured error.  A Consumer <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> exceed
          runtime.concurrency simultaneous instances.  The retry policy is controlled
          by max_retries and retry_backoff (fixed, linear, or exponential; default
          exponential).
        </t>
        <t>
          The runtime.async_execution flag enables a Consumer to return a job ID
          immediately and execute in the background.  The runtime.queue field names
          a work queue for async execution.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="telemetry" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Telemetry</name>
        <t>
          The agent.telemetry block declares OpenTelemetry <xref target="OTEL"/>
          configuration.  A Consumer with telemetry.tracing set to true
          <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> emit the following spans per agent run:
        </t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>aaif.agent.run (root) — with agent.id, agent.name, agent.version, model.provider, model.name attributes.</li>
          <li>aaif.agent.tool_call (child) — with tool.name, tool.protocol, tool.endpoint.</li>
          <li>aaif.agent.llm_call (child) — with llm.model, llm.provider, llm.input_tokens, llm.output_tokens.</li>
          <li>aaif.agent.memory_read and aaif.agent.memory_write — with memory.scope, memory.backend.</li>
          <li>aaif.agent.handoff — with target_agent.id, pass_context.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          The telemetry.otlp_endpoint field specifies the OTLP collector endpoint.
          If omitted, the Consumer falls back to its platform default.  W3C Trace
          Context <xref target="W3C-TRACE"/> propagation uses the header named in
          telemetry.trace_context_header (default "traceparent").
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="evaluation" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Evaluation</name>
        <t>
          The agent.evaluation block enables CI/CD quality gating.  The judge_model
          field names the LLM used to evaluate agent outputs (recommended to be at
          least as capable as the agent model).  The metrics[] array declares name and
          threshold pairs; standard metric names are: faithfulness, relevance,
          coherence, toxicity, hallucination_rate, task_completion, latency_ms,
          cost_usd_per_run, and tool_call_accuracy.  The test_cases[] array provides
          golden test inputs with expected outputs and rubric criteria.  A Consumer
          running CI evaluation <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> gate promotion to
          "status: active" on all threshold conditions being met.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="compliance-block" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Compliance Controls</name>
        <t>
          The agent.compliance block encodes legal and operational requirements that
          travel with the agent definition and cannot be silently dropped on import.
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>safety_level</dt>
          <dd>
            One of: minimal, standard, strict, regulated.  Governs Consumer behaviour
            on unsatisfied capabilities (see <xref target="capability-negotiation"/>)
            and constraint violations.
          </dd>
          <dt>data_residency</dt>
          <dd>
            One of: global, EU, US, UK, APAC, custom.  A Consumer
            <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> route only to LLM providers with data centres in
            the declared region.
          </dd>
          <dt>pii_handling</dt>
          <dd>
            One of: none, detect, anonymize, encrypt, reject.  Applied to memory items
            and tool outputs by the Consumer.
          </dd>
          <dt>audit_log</dt>
          <dd>
            Boolean.  When true, the Consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> maintain an
            append-only, tamper-evident log of all invocations.
          </dd>
          <dt>human_in_the_loop</dt>
          <dd>
            Object with enabled, trigger (a Condition), and timeout_seconds.  When
            enabled is true, the Consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> obtain human approval
            before executing any write tool call.  The trigger Condition allows scoping
            the gate to specific actions.
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="conditions" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Condition Expressions</name>
      <t>
        Several AAIF fields gate routing or execution: orchestration.subagents[].when,
        orchestration.handoff[].condition, events.triggers[].filter, and
        compliance.human_in_the_loop.trigger.  Each accepts a Condition value in one
        of two forms.
      </t>
      <t>
        The structured form (RECOMMENDED) is an object naming an expression language
        and an expression string:
      </t>
      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
{ "lang": "jsonpath", "expr": "$.task.type", "nl": "task type is code_review" }
]]></artwork>
      <t>Supported languages are:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>jsonpath — JSONPath query <xref target="RFC9535"/>; truthy if the result is non-empty.</li>
        <li>jmespath — JMESPath query; truthy if the result is truthy.</li>
        <li>cel — Common Expression Language boolean expression.</li>
        <li>jsonlogic — JsonLogic rule object evaluated against the payload.</li>
        <li>always — constant true (omit expr).</li>
        <li>never — constant false (omit expr).</li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        The optional nl field is a human-readable description for logs and UIs.  It
        is advisory; the structured expr is authoritative.
      </t>
      <t>
        The string form is also accepted for authoring convenience and backward
        compatibility.  A bare string is a hint only — different runtimes interpret it
        differently (or via an LLM) — and <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be relied upon for
        portable, reproducible routing.  Consumers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> emit a
        portability warning when routing on a string condition.
      </t>
      <t>
        A Consumer that supports a declared lang <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> evaluate the
        structured form deterministically and <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> fall back to
        LLM interpretation of nl.  A Consumer that does not support a declared lang
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> treat the condition as unsatisfied and apply the same
        behaviour as an unsatisfied required_capability per the agent's safety_level.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="conformance" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Conformance Levels</name>
      <t>
        AAIF defines seven cumulative conformance levels.  Conformance is self-certified
        against the public test suite (tests/conformance/ in the reference repository).
        There is no central certifying authority; credibility comes from the claim being
        machine-checkable against publicly available test fixtures.
      </t>
      <table align="center">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left">Level</th>
            <th align="left">Requirements</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>Core</td>
            <td>Validates against agent schema; agent.name and agent.goal present.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Tooled</td>
            <td>Core + at least one tool with parameters_schema.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Portable</td>
            <td>Tooled + constraints[] non-empty + resolvable tools[].endpoint.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Multi-agent</td>
            <td>Portable + orchestration.role declared + at least one subagent reference or handoff rule.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Observable</td>
            <td>Portable + telemetry.tracing true + at least one evaluation metric with threshold.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Enterprise</td>
            <td>Observable + compliance.safety_level declared + compliance.audit_log true + provenance.signature present.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Stateful</td>
            <td>Enterprise + required_capabilities[] includes state.checkpoint + Agent State checkpoints supported.</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <t>
        Conformance is per level and per direction.  A Producer at level L exports AAIF
        documents that validate against the schema and satisfy the level-L predicates.
        A Consumer at level L imports and honours every construct required at that level,
        including the normative <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> statements for that level.
      </t>
      <t>
        The Stateful level is deliberately advanced.  It introduces Agent State
        checkpoints, cross-platform migration, and streaming handoff (see
        <xref target="agent-state"/>).  Consumers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> achieve
        Enterprise conformance before implementing Stateful.  Enterprise conformance
        is independently meaningful and is not a prerequisite for Stateful.
      </t>
      <t>
        Conformance reports validate against schema/conformance-report.schema.json and
        are published at the well-known path /.well-known/aaif-conformance.json.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="capability-negotiation" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Capability Negotiation</name>
      <t>
        The agent.required_capabilities[] field declares what an agent requires from
        its executing runtime.  A Consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> check all declared
        capabilities before accepting an agent definition.
      </t>
      <t>
        Capabilities use a dot-namespaced string format: category.capability.
        Standard categories and example identifiers:
      </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>tool — tool.function, tool.mcp, tool.http, tool.openapi</li>
        <li>memory — memory.vector, memory.redis, memory.postgres, memory.pinecone, memory.qdrant</li>
        <li>orchestration — orchestration.parallel, orchestration.handoff, orchestration.pipeline, orchestration.consensus</li>
        <li>telemetry — telemetry.otel</li>
        <li>compliance — compliance.data_residency, compliance.hitl, compliance.audit_log</li>
        <li>auth — auth.vault</li>
        <li>io — io.streaming, io.async, io.batch</li>
        <li>state — state.checkpoint, state.restore</li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        The Consumer behaviour on an unsatisfied capability depends on the agent's
        compliance.safety_level:
      </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>minimal — log a warning and continue; the capability is silently skipped.</li>
        <li>standard — import the agent with a warning; disable the dependent feature.</li>
        <li>strict — <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> reject the import with a descriptive error listing unsatisfied capabilities.</li>
        <li>regulated — <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> reject the import; the failure <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be audit-logged.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        Consumers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> publish a machine-readable Platform Manifest
        at the well-known URL path /.well-known/aaif-manifest.json.  The manifest
        advertises the platform's supported capabilities, conformance level, AAIF
        versions supported, and an intake endpoint (platform.intake_endpoint) for
        posting agent definitions.  Orchestrators and CI/CD systems can fetch this
        manifest to perform capability negotiation before dispatching an agent.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="agent-state" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Agent State and Checkpointing</name>
      <t>
        AAIF v3 introduces a companion schema, agent-state.schema.json, for capturing,
        serialising, and restoring the complete execution state of a running agent.
        This enables three primary use cases: pause and resume on the same platform,
        cross-platform live migration, and crash recovery without full conversation
        replay.
      </t>

      <section anchor="state-document" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Agent State Document</name>
        <t>
          An Agent State document carries the following fields:
        </t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>state_id — a UUID uniquely identifying this checkpoint.</li>
          <li>agent_id — links to the originating agent definition.</li>
          <li>run_id — groups all checkpoints for one execution run.</li>
          <li>checkpoint_at — UTC timestamp of capture (ISO 8601).</li>
          <li>status — one of: running, paused, awaiting_approval, awaiting_tool_result, completed, failed, migrating.</li>
          <li>iteration — current agentic loop count; the Consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> enforce max_iterations on restore.</li>
          <li>pipeline_position — current_step, completed_steps[], remaining_steps[], current_subagent, parallel_slot.</li>
          <li>conversation[] — full message history; truncate from the oldest end on restore if the model context window is smaller.</li>
          <li>memory_snapshot[] — all in-scope memory items; vector embeddings are NOT serialised and are re-computed on restore.</li>
          <li>pending_tool_calls[] — in-flight or queued tool calls; the Consumer re-issues or marks them timed-out on restore.</li>
          <li>subagent_states[] — per-subagent summaries; active subagents export their own Agent State documents for deep migration.</li>
          <li>variables — named task-scope key-value pairs.</li>
          <li>approval_request — present when status is "awaiting_approval"; carries trigger description and timeout.</li>
          <li>error — present when status is "failed"; carries code, message, step, retries_remaining.</li>
          <li>provenance — source_platform, migration_token, and a SHA-256 hex checksum of the canonical JSON (excluding the checksum field).</li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section anchor="migration-protocol" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Cross-Platform Migration Protocol</name>
        <t>A cross-platform migration follows seven steps:</t>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
          <li>Source platform captures Agent State (status "paused" or "migrating").</li>
          <li>Source platform issues a short-lived migration_token (signed, expiry at most 15 minutes).</li>
          <li>Agent State document is transferred to the receiving platform out-of-band (API, file, message queue).</li>
          <li>Receiving platform verifies the SHA-256 checksum, the migration_token signature, and that agent_id matches a known agent definition.</li>
          <li>Receiving platform imports the state: loads memory, restores conversation, resumes at pipeline_position.current_step.</li>
          <li>Receiving platform re-issues pending_tool_calls still in-flight or marks them timed-out.</li>
          <li>Execution resumes.</li>
        </ol>
      </section>

      <section anchor="streaming-handoff" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Streaming Handoff Wire Format</name>
        <t>
          For uninterrupted mid-generation migration, AAIF v3 defines a streaming
          handoff wire format:
        </t>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
Content-Type: application/x-aaif-handoff+ndjson
]]></artwork>
        <t>
          Each line is a newline-delimited JSON object with a "type" discriminator.
          Message types are: handoff_init, context_chunk, memory_item, pipeline_state,
          pending_tool, subagent_ref, handoff_complete, and handoff_error.
        </t>
        <t>
          The stream <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be transmitted over TLS (HTTPS or WSS);
          plaintext streaming handoffs are non-conformant.  The receiving Consumer
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> verify the migration_token in the handoff_init message
          before processing subsequent messages.  If a handoff_error message is received,
          the Consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> discard all accumulated state and
          <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> resume execution.  The SHA-256 checksum in
          handoff_complete <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be verified against the reconstructed
          Agent State before execution resumes.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="binary-encoding" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Binary Encoding</name>
      <t>
        AAIF documents are canonically JSON <xref target="RFC8259"/>.  For
        bandwidth-constrained transports (embedded runtimes, edge deployments,
        high-throughput agent mesh), implementations <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> encode
        AAIF documents as CBOR (Concise Binary Object Representation)
        <xref target="RFC8949"/>.  The logical structure, field names, enum values,
        and all constraints of the JSON schemas apply without modification to
        CBOR-encoded documents.  The media type for CBOR-encoded AAIF documents is:
      </t>
      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
application/cbor; profile="https://schemacommons.org/SC-006/cbor"
]]></artwork>
      <t>
        Implementations <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> use integer keys as a compression
        scheme; field names remain UTF-8 text strings so JSON round-trips are lossless.
        Any Consumer claiming AAIF conformance at Portable level or above that accepts
        CBOR-encoded definitions <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> also accept the equivalent JSON
        encoding and produce identical behaviour.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="extension-registries" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Extension Registries</name>
      <t>
        AAIF has several open extension points where new values arise regularly: LLM
        providers, runtime capabilities, condition languages, vault providers, memory
        backends, and tool protocols.  Rather than requiring a schema version change
        for each new value, AAIF maintains community registries modelled on IANA's
        expert-review and specification-required registration policies.
      </t>
      <t>
        Each registry is a machine-readable JSON file validated against a registry
        meta-schema.  The schema enum for each extension point is a convenience
        subset of the registry; registered values with status "standard" are conformant
        even if not yet reflected in the schema enum.  Values in neither the enum nor
        the registry <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use the documented escape hatch (model.provider
        "custom" with provider_id, or x- extension keys at the document root) rather
        than inventing unregistered bare enum values.
      </t>
      <t>
        The six registries, their extension points, and registration policies are:
      </t>
      <table align="center">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left">Registry</th>
            <th align="left">Extension point</th>
            <th align="left">Policy</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr><td>providers.json</td><td>model.provider</td><td>Specification Required</td></tr>
          <tr><td>capabilities.json</td><td>required_capabilities[]</td><td>Expert Review</td></tr>
          <tr><td>condition-languages.json</td><td>Condition lang</td><td>Specification Required</td></tr>
          <tr><td>vault-providers.json</td><td>auth.vault_ref.provider</td><td>Specification Required</td></tr>
          <tr><td>memory-backends.json</td><td>memory[].backend</td><td>Specification Required</td></tr>
          <tr><td>tool-protocols.json</td><td>tools[].protocol</td><td>Standards Action</td></tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <t>
        Registration policies follow IANA conventions:
        First Come First Served (unique identifier and one-line description),
        Specification Required (stable public specification or documentation URL),
        Expert Review (Editor sign-off confirming orthogonality and scope), and
        Standards Action (normative schema change in a new MINOR version).
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="relationship-prior-art" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Relationship to Prior Art</name>
      <t>
        Before drafting this section, the editors searched specifically for an
        existing standard defining a portable, vendor-neutral agent <em>definition</em>
        document — the thing AAIF itself is.  No such standard was found.  The
        frameworks and protocols discussed below each address an adjacent problem,
        but none of them defines the complete, importable agent record that AAIF
        defines.  That absence is stated plainly here, rather than overstated or
        replaced with invented modesty about non-existent competitors.
      </t>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>Model Context Protocol (MCP)</dt>
        <dd>
          MCP <xref target="MCP"/> standardises how an agent invokes external tools
          — the wire protocol for tool calls.  It does not specify what an agent is,
          how it routes to an LLM, how it manages memory, or how it orchestrates
          subagents.  AAIF explicitly incorporates MCP as one of its four supported
          tool protocols.  The two specifications are complementary: MCP is the tool
          cable; AAIF is the agent blueprint.  Separately, the MCP project's own
          published roadmap <xref target="MCP-ROADMAP"/> (dated 2026-03-05) lists
          "audit trails and observability" as an acknowledged, currently unsolved
          Enterprise Readiness gap.  That is honest evidence that the agent ecosystem
          has more than one unsolved fragmentation problem; it is evidence of
          fragmentation generally, not specifically of the portable-agent-definition
          gap that AAIF addresses, and is cited here only for the former.
        </dd>
        <dt>A2A Agent Card</dt>
        <dd>
          The A2A Agent Card is a minimal discovery document advertising an agent's
          identity, capability tags, and endpoint URL.  It is deliberately thin by
          design.  An AAIF definition carries a superset of Agent Card information and
          can generate a conformant Agent Card.  A2A addresses agent-to-agent runtime
          messaging; AAIF addresses portable agent definition.
        </dd>
        <dt>OpenAI Assistants API</dt>
        <dd>
          The Assistants API is expressive within the OpenAI platform but is bound to
          a specific vendor's runtime and API surface.  AAIF can express the same
          concepts portably across providers.  A bidirectional reference converter
          between OpenAI Assistants format and AAIF is provided in the tooling
          repository.
        </dd>
        <dt>Agent Persistent State Profile (APS)</dt>
        <dd>
          draft-gaikwad-aps-profile-00 <xref target="APS"/> is an active IETF
          individual draft specifying a storage <em>service class</em> — an
          "AgentPersistentState" usage class with a versioned
          "PersistentStateLineOfService" schema, bound non-normatively to the SNIA
          Swordfish/Redfish storage-management standards, covering crash consistency,
          cryptographic erasure tied to identity, vector-index workloads, and
          Kubernetes/CSI integration.  APS operates at the storage-infrastructure
          layer: it describes how a storage backend advertises itself as suitable for
          hosting agent state.  AAIF's Agent State schema (<xref target="agent-state"/>)
          operates at the document layer: it describes the portable application-level
          record — conversation history, memory snapshot, pipeline position, pending
          tool calls, subagent states — captured from a running agent for pause,
          resume, or migration between runtimes.  The two are complementary, not
          competing: an AAIF Agent State document is the kind of payload that could be
          persisted on an APS-class volume.  AAIF takes no position on, and has no
          dependency on, the storage layer beneath a checkpoint.
        </dd>
        <dt>OpenTelemetry GenAI Semantic Conventions and OpenInference</dt>
        <dd>
          AAIF's telemetry block (<xref target="telemetry"/>) intentionally does not
          define its own span or event semantics.  Two real, overlapping conventions
          already exist: the OpenTelemetry GenAI semantic conventions
          <xref target="OTEL-GENAI"/> (<tt>gen_ai.*</tt> span attributes and an
          <tt>invoke_agent</tt> to <tt>chat</tt>/<tt>execute_tool</tt> span tree;
          experimental as of March 2026 but already emitted or instrumented by
          LangChain, CrewAI, AutoGen, and AG2, and consumed natively by Datadog,
          Honeycomb, and New Relic), and OpenInference <xref target="OPENINFERENCE"/>
          (Arize AI's OTel-based convention with ten span kinds: LLM, EMBEDDING,
          RETRIEVER, RERANKER, TOOL, CHAIN, AGENT, GUARDRAIL, EVALUATOR, PROMPT).  AAIF
          defers span-attribute semantics to whichever of these the executing runtime
          already speaks, rather than standardising a third, competing vocabulary.
          Agent observability and audit-event vocabularies more broadly are out of
          scope for this document; see the external prior-art note referenced from the
          Schema Commons repository for that adjacent discussion.
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
        Consumers <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> treat imported tools[].endpoint values as
        untrusted input and apply capability gating before activating any tool.
        An AAIF document from an unknown source could declare a tool endpoint pointing
        to an attacker-controlled server.
      </t>
      <t>
        Secrets <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> appear inline in AAIF documents.  The
        auth.env_var and auth.vault_ref fields name where the Consumer resolves the
        secret; they carry a reference, not the credential itself.  Tools that carry
        inline credential values in any field violate this specification and
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be rejected.
      </t>
      <t>
        The constraints[] array <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be enforced by the Consumer.
        A Consumer that silently drops a constraint is in violation of this
        specification and may permit harmful agent behaviour.
      </t>
      <t>
        Consumers <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be alert to prompt injection in
        context[type=url] values fetched at runtime.  Content retrieved from
        declared URLs <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be sanitised or sandboxed before
        injection into the agent's context window.
      </t>
      <t>
        The compliance.data_residency field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be respected.
        Routing an agent to a provider whose data centres are outside the declared
        region violates the compliance contract and may have legal consequences.
      </t>
      <t>
        Agent State documents contain conversation history and memory contents, which
        may include personally identifiable information (PII).  The same pii_handling
        policy declared in the agent definition <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be applied to
        Agent State documents at rest and in transit.  Agent State documents
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be transmitted over an encrypted channel.
      </t>
      <t>
        The migration_token in Agent State documents and streaming handoffs
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a signed, short-lived token with an expiry of at most
        15 minutes.  The receiving Consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> verify the token
        signature before accepting the state.  The SHA-256 checksum
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be verified before restoring state; a mismatch indicates
        tampering or corruption and the import <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be rejected.
      </t>
      <t>
        The provenance.signature field carries a Base64-encoded Ed25519 signature
        over the canonical JSON of the agent definition.  Consumers receiving agents
        from untrusted or third-party sources <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> verify this
        signature before execution.
      </t>
      <t>
        The stack_trace field in Agent State error blocks <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be
        stripped before exporting a checkpoint to an external platform to avoid
        disclosing implementation details.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="iana" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>

      <section anchor="iana-media-type" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Media Type Registration</name>
        <t>
          This document requests registration of the following media type with IANA.
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Type name</dt><dd>application</dd>
          <dt>Subtype name</dt><dd>x-aaif-handoff+ndjson</dd>
          <dt>Required parameters</dt><dd>None.</dd>
          <dt>Optional parameters</dt><dd>None.</dd>
          <dt>Encoding considerations</dt>
          <dd>UTF-8 newline-delimited JSON (NDJSON); each line is a JSON object.</dd>
          <dt>Security considerations</dt>
          <dd>See <xref target="security"/> of this document.  The stream MUST be transmitted over TLS.</dd>
          <dt>Interoperability considerations</dt>
          <dd>Recipients MUST verify the migration_token and SHA-256 checksum before processing.</dd>
          <dt>Published specification</dt><dd>This document.</dd>
          <dt>Applications that use this media type</dt>
          <dd>
            AAIF-conforming runtimes performing live agent state handoff during
            cross-platform migration of running AI agents.
          </dd>
          <dt>Fragment identifier considerations</dt><dd>None.</dd>
          <dt>Restrictions on usage</dt><dd>None.</dd>
          <dt>Author</dt><dd>Bob van Bussel, bob@observalytics.com</dd>
          <dt>Change controller</dt><dd>Schema Commons (https://github.com/Observalytics-SL/Frameworks)</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>

      <section anchor="iana-registries" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Future Registry Considerations</name>
        <t>
          AAIF currently maintains six community extension registries (providers,
          capabilities, condition languages, vault providers, memory backends, and
          tool protocols) as described in <xref target="extension-registries"/>.
          These registries are currently operated by the Schema Commons project.
          A future revision of this document or an accompanying document may request
          that IANA operate one or more of these registries under the appropriate
          IANA registration policies (Specification Required or Expert Review as
          indicated per registry).
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>

      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>

        <reference anchor="RFC2119"
                   target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119">
          <front>
            <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
            <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="S. Bradner">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="1997" month="March"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC2119"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="RFC8174"
                   target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc8174">
          <front>
            <title>Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC 2119 Key Words</title>
            <author initials="B." surname="Leiba" fullname="B. Leiba">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2017" month="May"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8174"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8174"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="RFC8259"
                   target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc8259">
          <front>
            <title>The JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) Data Interchange Format</title>
            <author initials="T." surname="Bray" fullname="T. Bray" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2017" month="December"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="STD" value="90"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8259"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8259"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="RFC8949"
                   target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc8949">
          <front>
            <title>Concise Binary Object Representation (CBOR)</title>
            <author initials="C." surname="Bormann" fullname="C. Bormann">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="P." surname="Hoffman" fullname="P. Hoffman">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2020" month="December"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="STD" value="94"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8949"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8949"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="RFC9535"
                   target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc9535">
          <front>
            <title>JSONPath: Query Expressions for JSON</title>
            <author initials="S." surname="Gössner" fullname="S. Gössner">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="G." surname="Normington" fullname="G. Normington">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="C." surname="Bormann" fullname="C. Bormann">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2024" month="February"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9535"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9535"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="JSON-SCHEMA"
                   target="https://json-schema.org/draft/2020-12">
          <front>
            <title>JSON Schema: A Media Type for Describing JSON Documents</title>
            <author initials="A." surname="Wright" fullname="A. Wright">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="H." surname="Andrews" fullname="H. Andrews">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2022"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

      </references>

      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>

        <reference anchor="RFC5545"
                   target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5545">
          <front>
            <title>Internet Calendaring and Scheduling Core Object Specification (iCalendar)</title>
            <author initials="B." surname="Desruisseaux" fullname="B. Desruisseaux" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2009" month="September"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5545"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC5545"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="MCP"
                   target="https://modelcontextprotocol.io">
          <front>
            <title>Model Context Protocol</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Anthropic</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2024"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="OTEL"
                   target="https://opentelemetry.io/docs/specs/">
          <front>
            <title>OpenTelemetry Specification</title>
            <author>
              <organization>OpenTelemetry</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2024"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="W3C-TRACE"
                   target="https://www.w3.org/TR/trace-context/">
          <front>
            <title>Trace Context</title>
            <author>
              <organization>W3C</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2021"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="APS"
                   target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-gaikwad-aps-profile/">
          <front>
            <title>Agent Persistent State Profile (APS)</title>
            <author fullname="Gaikwad, et al.">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2026"/>
          </front>
          <refcontent>Work in Progress</refcontent>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-gaikwad-aps-profile-00"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="OTEL-GENAI"
                   target="https://opentelemetry.io/docs/specs/semconv/gen-ai/">
          <front>
            <title>Semantic Conventions for Generative AI Systems</title>
            <author>
              <organization>OpenTelemetry</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2026"/>
          </front>
          <refcontent>Experimental</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="OPENINFERENCE"
                   target="https://github.com/Arize-ai/openinference">
          <front>
            <title>OpenInference Semantic Conventions</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Arize AI</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2026"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="MCP-ROADMAP"
                   target="https://modelcontextprotocol.io/development/roadmap">
          <front>
            <title>Model Context Protocol Roadmap</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Model Context Protocol</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2026" month="March" day="5"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

      </references>
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
